Guide to the Katherine Mayo Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Katherine Mayo papers
1835-1968
1918-1940
MS 345
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
27.5
(69 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, research materials, and miscellanea documenting the personal life and literary career of Katherine Mayo, an author of several historical and investigative articles, essays, and books from 1896 to 1940. Correspondence files document the detailed literary research Mayo conducted and the strong public reaction generated by her writings. This is particularly true for such works as Justice to All (1917), The Isles of Fear (1925), and Mother India (1927). Diaries provide sporadic information on the daily activities of Mayo, while writings include drafts of many works. Photographs and research materials further detail the foreign travels (South America, India, Philippines) and subsequent literary works produced by Mayo. Scrapbooks contain reviews and commentary relating to Mayo's publications. The papers provide information on such diverse such diverse topics as life in India, the Philippine Islands, and South America; the Pennsylvania State Police; George Washington; the Y.M.C.A. during World War I; war veterans of World War I; and the narcotics trade.
Mayo, Katherine, 1868?-1940
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of M. Moyca Newell, 1951-1962, and Mr. and Mrs. Richard W. Meade, 1962.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1898-1968. II. Diaries, 1886-1955. III. Essays and Newspaper Articles, 1890-1941. IV. Books, 1917-1940. V. Photographs and Miscellanea, 1835-1940.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, diaries, writings, photographs, scrapbooks, research materials, and miscellanea documenting the personal life and literary career of Katherine Mayo, an author of several historical and investigative articles, essays, and books from 1896-1940.
Correspondence files document the detailed literary research Mayo conducted, and the strong public reaction generated by her writings. This is particularly true for the books: Justice to All (1917), The Isles of Fear (1925), and Mother India (1927). Diaries provide sporadic information on the daily activities of Mayo, while her writings include drafts of many works. Photographs and research materials further detail the foreign travels (South America, India, the Philippine Islands) and subsequent literary works produced by Mayo. Scrapbooks contain reviews and commentary relating to Mayo's publications. The papers provide information on such diverse topics as life in India, the Philippine Islands, and South America; the Pennsylvania State Police; George Washington; the Y.M.C.A. during World War I; war veterans of World War I; and the narcotics trade.
The Katherine Mayo Papers (27.50 linear ft.) are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1898-1968; II. Diaries, 1886-1955; III. Essays and Newspaper Articles, 1890-1941; IV. Books, 1917-1940; and V. Photographs and Miscellanea, 1835-1940.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, 1898-1968, is arranged in chronological order and contains the incoming correspondence of Katherine Mayo (1898-1940) and M. Moyca Newell (ca. 1910-1968). The bulk of correspondence pertains to Katherine Mayo, and specificially her literary work on such books as Justice to All (1917), The Standard Bearers (1918), Mounted Justice (1922), Isles of Fear (1925), Mother India (1927), and Soldiers, What Next? (1934). Letters from publishers and individuals who read Mayo's works are included in this series.
Letters relating to Mayo's most familiar work, Mother India (1927), include correspondence from government figures in India, Great Britain, and the United States. This work elicited international comment and controversy, and both praise and condemnation, for its detailed view of Indian society. An earlier work by Mayo, Isles of Fear (1925), which examined life in the Philippine Islands, created a similar although less vocal reaction, as did her writings on the New York and Pennsylvania state police forces: Justice to All (1917), The Standard Bearers (1918), and Mounted Justice (1922). Soldiers, What Next?, published in 1934, also engendered a degree of controversy, as Mayo openly criticized the treatment of military veterans in the United States.
Prior to Mayo's success as a literary figure she was employed by Oswald Garrison Villard to conduct extensive field research for his biography of John Brown. Letters from Villard (ca. 1907-1913) detail Mayo's exhaustive research and include his encouragement regarding her own literary career. Letters from Harvard University's Peabody Museum and the Entomological News of Philadelphia (ca. 1900-1907) concern Mayo's work for those organizations. She lived with her father in South America during the early 1900s, and contracted to collect Indian relics and insect specimens.
Series II, DIARIES, 1886-1955, contains several volumes of diaries maintained by Katherine Mayo and M. Moyca Newell from 1886-1955. The diaries offer few insights into the thoughts of Mayo and Newell; rather, these volumes tend to briefly summarize the appointments and activities of a particular year or years.
Series III, ESSAYS AND NEWSPAPER ARTICLES, 1890-1941, contains drafts and printed copies of many of Mayo's first literary works. Mayo's work was published in such popular magazines and journals of the day as: Atlantic Monthly, Scribner's, The Outlook, and Nash's. Many of these essays formed the foundation (or an actual component) of Mayo's books.
Series IV, BOOKS, 1917-1939, contains manuscripts, notes, and photographs used in the research and writing of Mayo's books. Scrapbooks containing book reviews and speaking engagements are also arranged in this series. Several scrapbooks for Mother India (1927), in boxes thirty-seven through forty-one, document the widespread attention that book received.
Series V, PHOTOGRAPHS AND MISCELLANEA, 1835-1940, contains personal photographs of Mayo, including several portraits. Miscellanea includes a variety of ephemera, such as an autograph book; an account book of James Mayo, Katherine's father, dated 1835-1838; and a piece of the rope allegedly used to hang John Brown.
The Mayo Papers were donated to Yale University Library by M. Moyca Newell, 1951-1962, and Mr. and Mrs. Richard W. Meade, 1962.
Biographical / Historical
Katherine Mayo was born in Ridgeway, Pennsylvania, on January 24, 1867. She died in Bedford Hills, New York, on October 9, 1940. Mayo published several articles, essays, and books based on her travels and literary investigations from 1896-1938, including works on India and World War I. Mayo published articles in the New York Evening Post, Atlantic Monthly, and Scribner's Magazine, sometimes under the pen name Katherine Prence. She assisted Oswald Garrison Villard in the preparation of John Brown (1910), and Horace White in the preparation of Life of Lyman Trumbull (1913). Mayo wrote Justice to All (1917), The Standard Bearers (1918), That Damn Y (1920), Mounted Justice (1922), The Isles of Fear (1925), Mother India (1927), Volume II (1931), Slaves of the Gods (1929), Soldiers, What Next? (1934), The Face of Mother India (1935), and General Washington's Dilemma (1938). She was researching a book on the narcotics traffic at the time of her death. Mayo travelled extensively to research her literary topics, often in the company of her close friend and collaborator, M. Moyca Newell.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Child marriage -- India; Narcotics; Opium; Police, State -- New York (State); Police, State -- Pennsylvania; Veterans -- United States; Women authors, American; Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Men's Christian Associations; Asia; India -- Description and travel; India -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1947; India -- History -- British occupation, 1765-1947; India -- Politics and government -- 1765-1947; Pennsylvania -- History, Local; Philippines -- Description and travel; Authors; Astor, Nancy Witcher Langhorne Astor, Viscountess, 1879-1964; Aydelotte, Frank, 1880-1956; Babbitt, Edwin Burr, 1862-1939; Baldwin, Stanley Baldwin, Earl, 1867-1947; Batchelder, Charles C., 1867-1946; Brown, John, 1810-1882; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938; Disney, Walt, 1901-1966; Gandhi, Mahatma, 1869-1948; Gunther, John, 1901-1970; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972; Hughes, Rupert, 1872-1956; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936; Lothian, Philip Henry Kerr, Marquis of, 1882-1940; Lutyens, Emily, Lady, 1874-1964; Lyttleton, Edith Sophy Balfour, 1865-1948; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964; Masefield, John, 1878-1967; Maurois, André, 1885-1967; Mayo, Katherine, 1868?-1940; Newell, Marjorie Moyca; Osmeña, Sergio, 1878-1961; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950; Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Edward Reilly), 1900-1949; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Sullivan, Mark, 1874-1952; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Willert, Arthur, Sir, 1882-1973; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927
- Correspondence, 1898-1968; Series I; 4.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence arranged chronologically.
  - 1898 - 1916 March (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
  - 1916 April - 1918 February (Box 2, Folder 11-16)
  - 1918 March - 1920 (Box 3, Folder 17-23)
  - 1921 - 1925 August (Box 4, Folder 24-31)
  - 1925 September - 1927 November (Box 5, Folder 32-40)
  - 1927 December - 1928 June (Box 6, Folder 41-47)
  - 1928 July - 1930 July (Box 7, Folder 48-55)
  - 1930 August - 1933 (Box 8, Folder 56-67)
  - 1934 - 1935 June (Box 9, Folder 68-75)
  - 1935 July - 1938 May (Box 10, Folder 76-86)
  - 1938 June - 1968 (Box 11, Folder 87-96)
  - undated (Box 11, Folder 97-99)
- Diaries, 1886-1955; Series II; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  This series contains the diaries of Katharine Mayo and M. Moyca Newell arranged in chronological order.
  - Mayo, 1886 (Box 12, Folder 100)
  - Mayo, 1895 (Box 12, Folder 101)
  - Mayo, 1902 (Box 12, Folder 102)
  - Newell, 1903 (Box 12, Folder 103)
  - Mayo, 1908-1910 (Box 12, Folder 104)
  - Newell, 1909-1911 (Box 13, Folder 105)
  - Mayo, 1911-1919 (Box 13, Folder 106-109)
  - Newell, 1919 (Box 13, Folder 110)
  - Mayo, 1920 (Box 14, Folder 111)
  - Mayo, 1923-1926 (Box 14, Folder 112-114)
  - Mayo, 1928-1929 (Box 14, Folder 115)
  - Mayo, 1931-1940 (Box 15, Folder 116-120)
  - Mayo, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 121)
  - Newell, 1941-1950 (Box 16, Folder 122-124)
  - Newell, 1941-1945 (Box 16, Folder 123)
  - Newell, 1946-1950 (Box 16, Folder 124)
  - Newell, 1951-1955 (Box 17, Folder 125)
- Essays and Newspaper Articles, 1890-1941; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series is arranged in two sections: Essays (1890-1941) and Newspaper articles (1894-1935).
  Each section is arranged chronologically.
  - Essays
    - 1890-1900 (Box 18, Folder 126-127)
    - [ca. 1890-1910] (Box 18, Folder 128)
    - 1900-1910 (Box 18, Folder 129)
    - [ca. 1900-1910] (Box 18, Folder 130)
    - 1900-1910 (Box 18, Folder 131)
    - [ca. 1900-1910] (Box 18, Folder 132)
    - 1906 (Box 18, Folder 133)
    - 1910-1912 (Box 19, Folder 134-135)
    - [ca. 1913-1917] (Box 19, Folder 136)
    - 1917-1922 (Box 19, Folder 137)
    - [ca. 1919] (Box 19, Folder 138)
    - 1920-1928 (Box 19, Folder 139)
    - 1923 (Box 19, Folder 140)
    - [ca. 1927-1932] (Box 19, Folder 141)
    - [ca. 1930] (Box 19, Folder 142)
    - 1930-1935 (Box 20, Folder 143)
    - 1941 (Box 20, Folder 144)
    - undated (Box 20, Folder 145)
  - Newspaper articles
    - 1894-1907 (Box 21, Folder 146)
    - 1910-1935 (Box 21, Folder 147a-h)
- Books, 1917-1939; Series IV; 18 linear feet (44 boxes)
  This series contains manuscripts, notes, photographs, and scrapbooks relating to the volumes Katherine Mayo authored from 1917-1939.
  Material is arranged by the title of each volume, in chronological order of publication.
  - Justice to All, 1917
    - Manuscript: The Black Hussars (Box 22, Folder 148)
    - Minutes: Committee for New York State Police (Box 22, Folder 149)
    - Photographs (Box 22, Folder 150-153)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 24, Box 25, Box 23, Folder 154-157, Box 26)
  - The Standard Bearers, 1918: manuscripts (Box 27, Folder 158-163)
  - That Damn Y, 1920
    - Photographs (Box 28, Folder 164-167)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 28, Folder 168-169)
  - Mounted Justice, 1922: manuscript (Box 29, Folder 170)
  - Isles of Fear, 1925
    - Clippings, 1923 (Box 30, Folder 171)
    - Photographs, 1923 (Box 30, Folder 172)
    - Scrapbooks, 1925, undated (Box 32, Box 31, Folder 173-175)
  - Mother India, 1927
    - Manuscripts: final draft (Box 33, Folder 176-179)
    - Notes (Box 36, Box 35, Box 34, Folder 180-203)
    - Scrapbooks (Box 39, Box 38, Box 37, Folder 204-213, Box 41, Box 40)
    - Miscellanea
      - Notes (Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 42, Folder 214-242)
      - Clippings (Box 46, Folder 243-244)
      - Articles (Box 46, Folder 245)
      - Unidentified (Box 46, Folder 246-249)
  - Slaves of the Gods, 1929: manuscripts (Box 47, Folder 250-253)
  - Soldiers, What Next?, 1934
    - Manuscripts
      - U.S.A. section (Box 48, Folder 254-278, Box 49)
      - English section (Box 50, Folder 279-287)
      - Italian section (Box 51, Folder 288-292)
      - French Section (Box 52, Folder 293-295)
      - German section (Box 52, Folder 296-297)
      - Final version (Box 53, Folder 298-300)
    - Notes (Box 54, Folder 301)
    - Photographs
      - English (Box 54, Folder 302-303)
      - French (Box 54, Folder 304)
      - Italian (Box 54, Folder 305)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 54, Folder 306)
    - Scrapbook, 1929-1934 (Box 55, Folder 307)
  - The Face of Mother India, 1935
    - Manuscripts (Box 56, Folder 308-316)
    - Photographs (Box 59, Box 57, Folder 317-334, Box 58)
  - George Washington's Dilemma, 1938
    - Manuscripts (Box 61, Box 60, Folder 335-350)
    - Photographs (Box 62, Folder 351)
    - Scrapbook (Box 62, Folder 352)
  - White Poison, 1939
    - Manuscripts (Box 64, Box 63, Folder 353-371, Box 65)
    - Notes (Box 65, Folder 372-376)
    - Related materials
      - Correspondence: British Legion (Box 65, Folder 377)
      - Notes: state medical boards (Box 65, Folder 378-379)
- Photographs and Miscellanea, 1835-1940; Series V; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series is arranged in two sections: Photographs and Miscellanea.
  - Photographs
    - Dutch Guinea (Box 66, Folder 380-381)
    - Europe
      - Spain and Italy, 1906-1913 (Box 67, Folder 382-383)
      - Miscellaneous, 1906 (Box 67, Folder 384)
    - Personal
      - Others (Box 68, Folder 385)
      - Portraits: Katherine Mayo (Box 68, Folder 386-387)
  - Miscellanea
    - Bibliography (Box 68, Folder 388)
    - Biographical sketches, 1940 (Box 68, Folder 389)
    - Clippings (Box 68, Folder 390-391)
    - Account book: Mayo, James, 1835-1838 (Box 69, Folder 392)
    - Address books (Box 69, Folder 393)
    - Autograph books (Box 69, Folder 394)
    - Rope: Brown, John (Box 69, Folder 395)
    - Specimen inventory: South America (Box 69, Folder 396)
    - Mailing lists (Box 69, Folder 397)
    - Portrait of Katherine Mayo by Frank Salisbury (Box 70)